Guide to the Records of the Office of the Assistant Dean of Washington Square College (Henry Noss) RG.19.0.1
New York University Archives
Records of the Office of the Assistant Dean of Washington Square College (Henry Noss)
1968-1969
New York University Archives
Washington Square College. Office of the Assistant Dean
RG.19.0.1
0.5 Linear Feet
The Records of the Office of the Assistant Dean of Washington Square College is comprised of correspondence, memoranda, and publications created and/or collected by Assistant Dean Henry Noss primarily during his 1966-68 tenure in that office. The collection in its entirety spans from 1956 to 1972. Collection materials deal mostly with programs instituted for the purpose of academic and financial student assistance/encouragement, such as Career Guidance (Box 1, Folder 1), College Scholarship Service (Box 1, Folder 5), and the Educational Opportunity Grant (Box 1, Folders 7-8).
Scope and Contents
The Records of the Office of the Assistant Dean of Washington Square College (Henry Noss) primarily consists of correspondence, memoranda and reports relating generally to the the various programs and activities of the Office. These programs have mostly to do with student affairs, such as the Center for International Studies (Box 1, Folder 3), College Bound Programs (Box 1, Folder 4), Educational Opportunity Grants (Box 1, Folders 7-8), College Work Study (Box 1, Folder 6), College Scholarship programs (Box 1, Folder 5) and Evening Classes/Adult Education (Box 1, Folder 10). There are news articles and correspondence dealing with the controversy over the appointment of John Hatchett to a post within the University (Box 1, Folder 11).
Arrangement
Current arrangement is alphabetical by category in a single series. Upon receipt for processing in 2013, the collection materials were foldered categorically, but appeared to be in no discernable order otherwise.
Biography of Henry H. B. Noss
Henry Noss received a B.A. from Franklin & Marshall College in 1926, an M.A. from Princeton University in 1929, and a Ph.D. from Princeton in 1960. He came to New York University in 1930 as an instructor. He achieved the rank of Assistant Professor sometime in the 1940s and Associate Professor in the 1950s. He was named Assistant Dean in 1962 and became a full professor in 1963. Noss was interested in the relations between science and the arts and lectured frequently on topics dealing with the intersection of the two. In 1947 he introduced an interdepartmental course on the history of science as a Visiting Lecturer at Smith College. He was also a student of ancient metallurgy and wrote a monograph entitled The Mystery of Native Copper in the Ancient World.
Hatchett, John F.; Stoddard, George Dinsmore, 1897-1981; James Buell Munn Scholarship Fund; Hester, James M., 1924-; Noss, Henry; Buckler, William E. (William Earl), 1924-1990
- Series I: Records of the Office of the Assistant Dean of Washington Square College (Henry Noss)
  - Career Guidance, 1960 - 1963 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Center for International Affairs and Development, 1959 - 1966 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Center for International Studies, 1968 - 1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - College Bound Program, 1966 - 1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - College Scholarship Service, 1963 - 1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - College Work Study Program, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Educational Support Program (ESP) Curriculum, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Evening Classes/Adult Education, 1963 -1965 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Hatchett Controversy, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - President Hester (Memoranda), 1963 - 1969 (Box 1, Folder 13)